Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Science Division Projects, 2014-2021
  - Physics
    - Samy, Nour. Prototype Field Deploy-able Environmental Background Radiation Monitoring Station, 2021; 2021-0122 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0122)
      According to an investigation conducted by the United Nations Scientific Committee on the Effects of Atomic Radiation in 1993, 80% of all radiation received by the human population on Earth is from natural radiation sources. There are only a handful of studies and detector networks dedicated to the collection of background radiation spectra and subsequent correlation with weather and environmental phenomenon. This paper describes the process of refurbishing and re-deploying a gamma spectrometer on campus grounds for constant and accurate energy spectrum collection to allow for statistical analysis and correlation with environmental data such as rainstorms and lunar cycles.
      Author provided keywords: Experimental Background Radiation Gamma Spectrometer Station
    - Shafi, Hanaan. Investigating the State of Conservation of Ancient Mummies and Bones Using Mobile NMR and CT, 2021; 2021-120 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0120)
      The aim of this project was to assess the state of conservation of a set of ancient mummies and bones by examining their proton depth profiles, acquired using mobile NMR. This was achieved by performing CPMG experiments on the samples, and using the T2 decay curves in order to arrive at a measure of proton density. For the skulls, it was found the skulls of the frozen mummies were particularly well-conserved. On the other hand, the tibia of Charlemagne and the left B16 tibia were found to be the best-conserved among the samples under consideration. The secondary aim was to determine whether the same information about the structural integrity of the bones could be ascertained from CT and mobile NMR. This was achieved by acquiring cross-sectional CT scans of the samples at the same locations where NMR measurements were made, and comparing the two. It was found that the two techniques do result in the same information about the proton density and consequently, the state of conservation. Considering the limitations of CT, mobile NMR was concluded to be a viable instrument to replace CT for cultural heritage purposes.
      Author provided keywords: NMR, CT, Mummies
    - Wrzosek, Ramon. Radio Quiet AGN in the North Ecliptic Pole, 2021; 2021-0123 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0123)
      We present initial results from the 4.8 GHz VLBA radio survey of the North Ecliptic Pole (NEP) deep field. An analysis of 12 VLBA sources with their IR counterparts shows a correlation between the radio/IR emissions and the physical properties of the AGN and their host galaxies. A ratio of 1to1 VLBA to JVLA flux densities indicates a compact source (parsec scale) produced the detected radio emission. Brightness temperatures (TB > 10^5 K) confirm an AGN is the main source of this emission. VLBA flux density lower than the JVLA flux density indicates the radio emission is distributed across the galaxy, in the kpc scale. These predictions agree with the IR colors classification of the WISE counterparts.
  - Psychology
    - Al Neyadi, Layla Mohamed Sultan Mohamed. Cross-Cultural Perceptions of the Hijab: How Middle Easterners and Westerners Respond to Veiled Women, 2014; 2014-0053; 126 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2014-0053)
      Major: Psychology
      Abstract: Numerous qualitative studies have investigated why Middle Eastern women may choose to veil. The work suggests that many women veil for reasons other than religious obligation. Some of their reasons include veiling as a means to protect their individuality and sense of agency, a claim in direct conflict with Western stereotypes of veiling as an oppressive and objectifying practice. Do these reports signal important cross-­‐cultural differences in a perceivers' spontaneous responses to veiled women? To address this issue, the current investigation explored the rapid objectification of veiled and unveiled women by Middle Eastern and Western perceivers, using two standard measures of implicit associations. While the results did not provide evidence of objectification, they signaled the dehumanization of veiled women across cultures. Both Middle Eastern and Western perceivers considered women who veiled as less human than non-­‐veiling women. In addition, Middle Easterners also dehumanized women more than Westerners, regardless of their headgear. A second task, however, did not support these conclusions, potentially due to poor test validity. The obtained results provide tentative evidence for cross-­‐cultural consistency as well as divergence regarding the perception of (veiled) women.
      Dehumanization; Objectification; Stereotypes (Social psychology); Discrimination; Hijab (Islamic clothing); Head Covers/Veils
    - Badwan, Iman R. Intergroup Contact and its Effect on Social Identification: The Case of Filipina Workers in the UAE, 2014; 2014-0048; 136 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2014-0048)
      Major: Psychology, Visual Arts
      Abstract: The possible effects of contact, relative to the interactions according to location, have been examined on group-based identities of Filipina women in Abu Dhabi and Manila. The study shows significant relationship between the increase ingroup national and religious identification with Filipinas and the increase in identification with Arabs in the host community, Abu Dhabi. However, the same relationship does not exist with Filipinas working in Manila. Although we do not measure contact directly, the results points to the possible influence of contact with outgroup members that can be explored in future studies.
      Social psychology; Philippines; Groups, Social; Social identity; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates
    - Kazemini, Sahar. Culture-Dependent Internal Face Processing, 2014; 2014-0057; 107 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2014-0057)
      Abstract: Decades of research on face recognition with Western observers suggest that during the processing of unfamiliar faces perceivers rely more strongly on external facial features (e.g., hair and face outline) than internal facial features (e.g., eyes and nose). Recent evidence indicates, however, that this processing preference may be culture-dependent. Egyptian perceivers, for instance, show the opposite face processing pattern; an effect argued to reflect their frequent exposure to faces void of external facial features (i.e., female faces covered by headscarves). To further examine this claim, spontaneous recognition accuracy for internal facial features was assessed, using a standard part-whole face recognition task, in Western perceivers living in New York and Middle Eastern perceivers living in Abu Dhabi. Accuracy scores were submitted to a 2 (perceiver culture: Western vs. Middle Eastern) x 2 (target face race: Caucasian vs. Arab) x 2 (face probe: part vs. whole) mixed measures analysis of variance. As predicted, Middle Eastern perceivers outperformed Westerners with regard to recognition accuracy. Merely on trials that required recognizing isolated face parts of Caucasian faces, both groups of perceivers performed equally well. Importantly, Middle Easterners also reported higher exposure to covered faces in everyday life than Westerners. In combination, these findings provide evidence that culture-specific face environments can impact basic aspects of face recognition.
      Face; Head Covers/Veils; Hijab (Islamic clothing); Facial recognition (Psychology); Cross-cultural comparison
    - Park, Hyun Kyung. Processing Code Switch in Highly Proficient Korean-English Bilinguals, 2014; 2014-0047; 115 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2014-0047)
      Abstract: Code switching is a cognitive aspect of bilingualism. Code switching has been linked to a processing cost, with the inhibitory mechanism in language selection leading to an asymmetrical switching cost in low proficiency bilinguals, but a symmetrical cost in high proficiency bilinguals. Given the limited literature on intra-sentential code switching that high proficiency bilinguals have been reported to do, as well as on bilinguals of genealogically distinct languages, this study used the self-paced reading paradigm to investigate the presence, extent, and symmetry of a switching cost in highly proficient Korean-English bilinguals. The results showed that there was no overall switching cost, but instead a marginal advantage when switching from Korean to English. Because there was no switching cost, there was no symmetry or asymmetry to be interpreted in light of the inhibitory mechanism.
      Code switching (Linguistics); Bilingualism; English language; Korean language; Language and languages
    - Haynes, Robert Clark III. Auditory Speech Priming as a Means of Exploring Linguistic Storage Mechanisms, 2015; 2015-0040; 3411 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2015-0040)
      Abstract: This paper examines theories of lexical access, particularly regarding morphological decomposition of spoken words. Two competing theories of lexical access, William Marslen-Wilson's Cohort theory, and James McClelland's and Jeffrey Elman's TRACE model, differ mainly in their treatment of phonology in lexical access. Marslen-Wilson (1994) has also posited that morphemes are the most basic unit of lexical storage. To test these, and other more recent models, we used a subliminal auditory speech priming method designed by Kouider and Dupoux (2005) to determine the roles of phonology, morphology, meaning, and lexicality is lexical access. We find no effect of morphology, and posit that lexical processing, beyond determining whether an utterance is a word, requires that utterances enter consciousness before unconscious parsing can take place. We also find an inhibitory effect of pseudowords, which suggests that lexical access is not a serial process and that familiarity with words may also play a role in processing.
      Morphological decomposition; Subliminal perception; Speeches; Morphology (Linguistics); Priming (Psychology)
    - Mohmad, Farah. Examining the relationship between motivation and aspiration: The effect of home and school environment on educational aspirations, 2015; 2015-0033; 3417 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2015-0033)
      Abstract: Previous studies demonstrated a relationship between motivation and aspirations in school-aged children (Mertens, 2012), the present study reveals the intricacies in this relationship. This study examines the effect of manipulating motivation on students' educational aspirations. Participants were 169 students in 5th, 7th, and 9th grade from schools in Chennai, India who completed a questionnaire that included two conditions: positive outcome focus (i.e., reaching the goal) and negative outcome focus (i.e., failing to reach the goal). After the manipulation, students reported their predicted performance levels during and after the school year. The results support our hypothesis of motivation having an effect on aspiration where students in the positive outcome focus condition reported having higher short-term and long-term aspirations. Our results also showed an interaction effect between motivation and perceived student support. Students who reported having low perceived student support had significantly higher short-term aspirations in the positive outcome focus condition than students in the negative outcome focus condition. The results might help school counselors and teachers to increase the motivation of students in secondary schools and therefore, increase their aspirations.
      Support systems, Social; Manipulation (Psychology); Affluence; Aspirations, Student; Motivation (Psychology)
    - Mészáros, Eszter. Comprehension of Verbal Negation in Early Childhood as a Cue to Logical Inferences., 2016; 2016-0033; 8018; English-learning infants were shown to have "no" in their active vocabulary for almost a year before they understand it as truth functional negation (e.g. Feiman et. al, under review). The present study investigated three hypotheses concerning the acquisition of truth functional negation cross-linguistically: 1) a conceptual shift is required; 2a) it is dependent on mastering sentence structure; 2b) negation is hard for children because of its conceptual and linguistic complexity. Experiment 1 compared Hungarian 20-month-olds' understanding of "nem" ( "no/not") and English-learning 20- and 24-month-olds' understanding of "no/not" through a search task. While English-learning 20-month-olds ignored the negative operator in negative trials, their Hungarian peers and American 24-month-olds were marginally above chance and performed better not only on negative but also on affirmative trials. Experiment 2 compared 18-month-old English- and Hungarian-learners' comprehension of nonexistence ("all gone"/"nincsen") through a task devised by Szabo and Kovacs (in preparation). While Hungarian infants performed better on the task, both groups' performance was above chance on the first test trial and overall. Results from experiment 1 and 2 suggest that Hungarian-learners are developmentally ahead of their English-learning peers on the comprehension of both affirmation and negation, ruling out hypothesis 1) and supporting hypothesis 2a). (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0033)
      English-learning infants were shown to have "no" in their active vocabulary for almost a year before they understand it as truth functional negation (e.g. Feiman et. al, under review). The present study investigated three hypotheses concerning the acquisition of truth functional negation cross-linguistically: 1) a conceptual shift is required; 2a) it is dependent on mastering sentence structure; 2b) negation is hard for children because of its conceptual and linguistic complexity. Experiment 1 compared Hungarian 20-month-olds' understanding of "nem" ( "no/not") and English-learning 20- and 24-month-olds' understanding of "no/not" through a search task. While English-learning 20-month-olds ignored the negative operator in negative trials, their Hungarian peers and American 24-month-olds were marginally above chance and performed better not only on negative but also on affirmative trials. Experiment 2 compared 18-month-old English- and Hungarian-learners' comprehension of nonexistence ("all gone"/"nincsen") through a task devised by Szabo and Kovacs (in preparation). While Hungarian infants performed better on the task, both groups' performance was above chance on the first test trial and overall. Results from experiment 1 and 2 suggest that Hungarian-learners are developmentally ahead of their English-learning peers on the comprehension of both affirmation and negation, ruling out hypothesis 1) and supporting hypothesis 2a).
    - Kim, Gagyung. Cross-Cultural Differences in the Perception of Facial Trustworthiness., 2016; 2016-0034; 8089; Previous research has shown that people habitually extract social information from faces. Yet, conflicting findings regarding cross-cultural consensus in face-based personality judgments have been reported in the literature. Using a reverse correlation task, the current study asked American and Emirati participants to make trustworthiness judgments in response to Arab and White faces. Results were analyzed using both quantitative and qualitative methods. A quantitative analysis of agreement rates within and across perceiver groups is suggestive of a perceiver culture by face race interaction. Furthermore, a qualitative inspection of composite faces based on participants' trustworthiness judgments revealed evidence in favor of both a main effect of perceiver culture as well as a perceiver culture by face race interaction. The findings add to a growing body of work that challenges the notion of high cross-cultural consensus in face-based personality judgments. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0034)
      Previous research has shown that people habitually extract social information from faces. Yet, conflicting findings regarding cross-cultural consensus in face-based personality judgments have been reported in the literature. Using a reverse correlation task, the current study asked American and Emirati participants to make trustworthiness judgments in response to Arab and White faces. Results were analyzed using both quantitative and qualitative methods. A quantitative analysis of agreement rates within and across perceiver groups is suggestive of a perceiver culture by face race interaction. Furthermore, a qualitative inspection of composite faces based on participants' trustworthiness judgments revealed evidence in favor of both a main effect of perceiver culture as well as a perceiver culture by face race interaction. The findings add to a growing body of work that challenges the notion of high cross-cultural consensus in face-based personality judgments.
    - Nadyukova, Iryna. Academic Achievement Motivation in the Context of Tertiary Education., 2016; 2016-0037; 8111; The study investigated similarities and differences in academic achievement motivation of students (N = 503) from three different contexts of tertiary education. The study examined how motivation to learn, future-oriented motivation and emotional component of motivation varies across public/private and local/international educational setting, gender and experimentally induced cognitive mindsets. Participants were randomly assigned to four conditions for the experimental mindset induction. Afterwards all participants responded to questionnaires about academic motivation. Female students in a local public setting scored significantly higher on emotional component of motivation than the male students. Furthermore, the female students in the deliberative mindset condition scored significantly higher on emotional component of motivation than the female students in neutral mindset condition and control group. The analysis of motivation to learn and future-oriented motivation revealed a consistent pattern of results, where the students from the local public setting differed significantly from the students from the local private and the international private settings. Main effects of gender showed that overall female students displayed higher motivation to learn, while male students scored higher on future-oriented motivation. The findings have implications for helping educators improve academic motivation of the students. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0037)
      The study investigated similarities and differences in academic achievement motivation of students (N = 503) from three different contexts of tertiary education. The study examined how motivation to learn, future-oriented motivation and emotional component of motivation varies across public/private and local/international educational setting, gender and experimentally induced cognitive mindsets. Participants were randomly assigned to four conditions for the experimental mindset induction. Afterwards all participants responded to questionnaires about academic motivation. Female students in a local public setting scored significantly higher on emotional component of motivation than the male students. Furthermore, the female students in the deliberative mindset condition scored significantly higher on emotional component of motivation than the female students in neutral mindset condition and control group. The analysis of motivation to learn and future-oriented motivation revealed a consistent pattern of results, where the students from the local public setting differed significantly from the students from the local private and the international private settings. Main effects of gender showed that overall female students displayed higher motivation to learn, while male students scored higher on future-oriented motivation. The findings have implications for helping educators improve academic motivation of the students.
    - Palfi, Dora. The effects of dopaminergic modulation on the stability of working memory representation., 2016; 2016-0032; 8139; Working Memory (WM), the temporary retention of information that was just experienced or just retrieved from long-term memory is thought to underlie goal-directed behavior. WM relies heavily on the prefrontal cortex (PFC), and specifically dopaminergic input to the PFC. Studies employing distractor stimulus in the delay period of WM tasks have indicated that the memory of the target stimulus can be corrupted by such distractors. The mediation of distracting effects may involve the PFC and the dopaminergic system. The aim of this research project is to quantify the effects of physiologically realistic dopamine modulation (via manipulations of reward) on the behavioral and neural effects of distraction during WM using behavioral modeling and magnetoencephalography (MEG). (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0032)
      Working Memory (WM), the temporary retention of information that was just experienced or just retrieved from long-term memory is thought to underlie goal-directed behavior. WM relies heavily on the prefrontal cortex (PFC), and specifically dopaminergic input to the PFC. Studies employing distractor stimulus in the delay period of WM tasks have indicated that the memory of the target stimulus can be corrupted by such distractors. The mediation of distracting effects may involve the PFC and the dopaminergic system. The aim of this research project is to quantify the effects of physiologically realistic dopamine modulation (via manipulations of reward) on the behavioral and neural effects of distraction during WM using behavioral modeling and magnetoencephalography (MEG).
    - Smoley, James. Does our trust of other races change with exposure?., 2016; 2016-0038; 8149; We make automatic judgements about the trustworthiness of an individual based on the appearance of their face. These trustworthiness judgements are important because they guide our decisions, such as approaching or avoiding an individual. Some research has been conducted on trustworthiness judgements made across racial groups. This research has found that raters of the same-race as a target face make significantly different trustworthiness judgements than other-race raters. This research has also suggested the differences in judgements could be due to experience with other races, but this has not been measured. In my research I will control for the experience of raters with other-races. I hypothesize that increased experience will strengthen the correlations of the trustworthiness judgements made by same-race and other-race raters. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0038)
      We make automatic judgements about the trustworthiness of an individual based on the appearance of their face. These trustworthiness judgements are important because they guide our decisions, such as approaching or avoiding an individual. Some research has been conducted on trustworthiness judgements made across racial groups. This research has found that raters of the same-race as a target face make significantly different trustworthiness judgements than other-race raters. This research has also suggested the differences in judgements could be due to experience with other races, but this has not been measured. In my research I will control for the experience of raters with other-races. I hypothesize that increased experience will strengthen the correlations of the trustworthiness judgements made by same-race and other-race raters.